Guide to the Jerome Epstein papers, 1877-1895,1915-2002
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Jerome Epstein papers
1877-1895, 1915-2002
C0262
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
8.0 linear ft.
The collection includes World War II military letters, photography equipment, newspapers, correspondence, scrapbooks, notebooks, audiotapes, 8mm film reels, and military badges. The collection contains material from 1877-1895 and 1915-2002.
Epstein, Jerome, 1925-2002
Box 1-7
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by L. Claire Kincannon in 2015.
Biographical Information
Born August 25, 1925 to Jerome and Rosella Epstein, Jerome Zachariah Epstein, Jr. attended Jefferson Public Schools until being accepted into Miami University in Oxford, Ohio in 1942. After attending Miami University in Oxford for one year, Epstein enlisted in the U.S. Army, August 10, 1943, and went into active service January 3, 1944. He was sent to Italy and served for seven months as a radio operator with the 110th Mountain Signal Company 10th Mountain Division located in the Northern Appennines and the Po Valley. Epstein was honorably discharged April 19, 1946 and was awarded two bronze service stars. After returning to civilian life, Epstein finished a 4-year program at University of Dayton. After college, he would go on to work at Western Iron and Steel, a family business. Jerome Epstein, Jr. died August 14, 2002.
Scope and Content
The collection includes photographs, photography equipment, newspapers, correspondence, scrapbooks, notebooks, audiotapes, 8mm film reels, and military badges. The collection is arranged into four series:
Series 1: World War II Era Items (1942-1946) includes photographs, maps, identification papers, travel books, and numerous letters.
Series 2: Photographs (1914-1998) includes photographs of Jerome Epstein, Jr., the Epstein family, negatives, photo albums, and photography equipment.
Series 3: Scrapbooks and Slides (1940-1954) includes color slides of the Epstein family, vacations, and spring flowers. It also includes many scrapbooks which contain post cards, newspaper clippings, and many World War II items.
Series 4: Epstein Family Items (1877-1895, 1915-2002) includes many items belonging to the Epstein family including financial documents, date books, newspapers clippings, Western Iron and Steel documents, and school documents.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series.
Series 1: World War II Era Items, 1942-1946 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Photographs, 1914-1998 (Boxes 3-10)
Series 3: Scrapbooks and Slides, 1940-1954 (Boxes 11-16)
Series 4: Epstein Family Items, 1877-1895, 1915-2002 (Boxes 17-22)
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center holds other collections that document World War II and postwar United States history, including the and the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Epstein, Jerome, 1925-2002
Subjects:
Letters.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; World War, 1939-1945.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Negatives.; Newspapers.; Photographs.; Slides.
Contents List
- Series 1: World War II Era Items, 1942-1946 (Boxes 1-2)
  This series includes photographs, maps, identification papers, travel books, and numerous letters.
  - Military Issue Pamphlets, Identification Cards, Photographs of Jerome Epstein, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - World War II Era Letters to Family, June 1942, January-July 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - World War II Era Letters to Family, August-December 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - World War II Era Letters to Family, January-June 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - World War II Era Letters to Family, July-December 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - World War II Era Letters to Family, January-April 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Discharge Papers, Identification Photos, Newspaper, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - English-Italian Dictionaries, Maps of Italy and Venice, Newspapers, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Discharge Papers and Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Military Service Records of Jerome Epstein, 1946-2015 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Travel Books for Venice, Italy, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1914-1998 (Boxes 3-10)
  This series includes photographs of Jerome Epstein, Jr., the Epstein family, negatives, photo albums, and photography equipment.
  - Photographs, Invitations, Playbills, and Newspaper Clippings, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Family, Artwork, 1940-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Family, Artwork, 1940-1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Family, Artwork, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Family, and Negatives, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Family, Negatives, Color Film Transparencies, 1943, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Family, Color Film Transparencies, 1947-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Color Film Transparencies from New York City, Marsha Bramson Wedding Announcement, May 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Negatives of Family Photographs, 1930-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Negatives of Family Photographs and Jerome Epstein, circa 1940-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Portrait of Rosella Epstein, Photographs, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Epstein Family Photo Album, circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and Remembrance Booklet, 1925,1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Jerome Epstein, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Epstein Family, Friends, Jerome Jr. and Rosella Epstein, 1895-1930, 1949-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein, Jr., and Family, 1944, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photo Album, circa 1930-1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Family and House, circa 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Family and House, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Family and House, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Family and House, 1978-1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Artwork and House, 1965, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Family and Vacation, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Vacation and House, circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Family, House, and Artwork, 1966, 1979, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Family, House, and Artwork, 1976-1977, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Family, House, and School, circa 1940, 1967, 1980-1994 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Family, Vacation, and House, 1965, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Family, Negatives, Letter from Jerome Epstein, circa 1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Family and House, circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Family and Vacation, circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Rosella Epstein and Family Vacation, circa 1960 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Jerome Epstein in Uniform, Family, and Vacation, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Saul Green, Jerome as a Child, Family, Jerome Sr. and Rosella Epstein, 1914, circa 1930-1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Epstein Family Photo Album, circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Vernon 8mm Camera and Photo Viewers, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Series 3: Scrapbooks and Slides, 1940-1954 (Boxes 11-16)
  This series includes color slides of the Epstein family, vacations, and spring flowers. It also includes many scrapbooks which contain post cards, newspaper clippings, and many World War II items.
  - Color Slides of Sea Isle, Miami, and Spring Flowers, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Color Slides of Sea Isle, Essex House, and Thanksgiving, 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Color Slides of Epstein Family, 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Color Slides of Epstein Family, 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Color Slides of New York City, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Color Slides of Epstein Family and House, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Color Slides of Sea Isle, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Color Film Transparencies, circa 1954 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Color Film Transparencies, circa 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Color Film Transparencies, 1953-1954 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Post Cards, circa 1950 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook of Post Cards, circa 1950 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of Post Cards, circa 1940-1950 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook of Playbills, circa 1930s (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Barker Music Box, Birthday Card to Jerome Epstein, circa 1940s (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Color Slides of Spring Flowers, circa 1950s (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Color Slides of New York City, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook Part I, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook Part II, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook Part III, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook Part IV, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook Part V, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook Part VI, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook of World War II Era Items, circa 1940s (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Series 4: Epstein Family Items, 1877-1895, 1915-2002 (Boxes 17-22)
  Includes many items belonging to the Epstein family including financial documents, date books, newspapers clippings, Western Iron and Steel documents, and school documents.
  - "The Daytonian", Dayton High School Yearbook, 1915 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - "The Daytonian", Dayton High School Yearbook, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - "The Daytonian", Dayton High School Yearbook, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - "The Daytonian", Dayton High School Yearbook, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - "The Cauldron", Frankfurt High school Yearbooks, 1912, 1913 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "The Cauldron", Frankfurt High school Yearbooks, 1914, 1917 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - "The Cauldron", Frankfurt High school Yearbooks, 1918, 1920 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Rosella Green School Record Book, Jerome Epstein University Diploma and Writings, 1915, circa 1950 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Newspapers and Clippings, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Name Tapes, Graduation Programs, Letters, Rosella Epstein Driver's License, 1940-1949 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Moses Epstein Financial Documents and Letters, Letters and Invitations to Rosella and Jerome Epstein, 1877-1915, 1943-1978 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Letters, Western Iron and Steel Co. Records, Invitations, 1942-1991 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Dayton Woman's Club Yearbook, Rosella Green Diploma, Spelling Book, 1915-1921 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Report Cards, Invitations, 1934-1944, 1945, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Jerome Epstein Sr. Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence of Jerome Epstein, Sr., Western Iron and Steel Co. Paperwork, 1951-1954 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Sympathy Cards and Donation Acknowledgements, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Sympathy Cards and Donation Acknowledgements, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Sympathy Cards and Donation Acknowledgements, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Sympathy Cards and Donation Acknowledgements, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Sympathy Cards and Donation Acknowledgements, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Date Books, Letters, Newspapers, University Documents, 1978-2002 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Record Books, Post Cards, Will of Louis Green, Hotel Receipts, 1953-1992 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Invoices, Tax Returns and Forms, Western Iron and Steel Co. Financial Documents, 1951-1955 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Temple Israel Service Programs, Letter to Jerome Epstein, Sr., 1894, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Rosella and Jerome Epstein, Sr. Correspondence, Western Iron and Steel Documents, 1948-1963 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Jerome Epstein High School Papers, Report Cards, Play Reviews, 1935-1943 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Jerome Epstein High School Papers, Play Scripts, School Newspaper, 1940-1945 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Jerome Epstein Writings, Scripts, 1941-1943 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets and User Manuals, circa 1950 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Poetry Collection, circa 1940-1950 (Box 22, Folder 6)